Finding Aid for Commission for Women (University of Michigan) records, 1989-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Commission for Women (University of Michigan) records 1989-1997
University of Michigan. Commission for Women.
0.4 linear feet
97126 Bimu 2
Commission established in 1971 to investigate discrimination against women. It preceded the university's Affirmative Action Office which was formed in 1972. Membership includes faculty, staff, and students. Records contain material from the 25th anniversary of the Commission for Women, including audio-visual items. Also includes mission and planning documents and retirement subcommittee records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Commission for Women (donor no. 8561 ) in 1997.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
TThe records are open to research.
The Commission for Women at the University of Michigan was established by President Robben Fleming in 1971 due to pressure from the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare to stop discrimination against female employees and staff. The University of Michigan's initial noncompliance to this demand resulted in $15 million in federal contracts being withheld from the University. The Commission for Women preceded the University's first Affirmative Action Office which was formed a year later.
Barbara Newell, Fleming's assistant and acting Vice President for Student Affairs created and lead the first commission. Although initially funded, the commission has been a volunteer organization since 1977 consisting of faculty, staff, and student representatives from across campus. In 1977, the commission merged with the Affirmative Action Office, which is responsible for compliance with federal statutes.
The Commission for Women primarily acts as an advocacy group, serving in an advisory role to the Affirmative Action Office and provides programs designed for the professional development of women. Over the years, the commission has tackled issues such as equal employment opportunities, equal compensation and benefits, and career development. The commission also convinced President Duderstadt to hold Town Meetings to discuss areas of concern to women on campus.
Currently, the Commission for Women is continuing as a volunteer organization, staffed by members of the university with the chair and co-chair changing somewhat annually. The commission supports the Michigan Agenda for Women and sees itself as a conduit between staff women and the university administration, working to provide different strategies toward improving the climate for women at the university.
The records are divided into three series. The Commission for Women Twenty-Fifth Anniversary series contains one folder of sample programs and invitations for the anniversary event which was held in 1996. The contents give a concise history of the organization and highlight the commission's most noteworthy activities.
A VHS video cassette of the anniversary festivities can also be found in the Audio Visual series. Another videotape contains the slide show Turnabout, which was also shown at the twenty-fifth anniversary celebration. Turnabout was originally produced and presented in the early 1970s in an effort to raise stereotyping consciousness. One last item in the Audio Visual series is an audio cassette tape of a brown bag luncheon, which featured Carol Hollenshead on the history of the Commission for Women and Laura Calkins who spoke about updating the book A Dangerous Experiment, a general history of women attending the University of Michigan.
Margaret Creger was chair of the commission from 1989 to 1991 and co-chair with Kathleen Alonozo from 1991 to 1992. Her records are held in the Margaret Creger Records series and contain correspondence regarding both the commission and the Commission for Women Retirement Subcommittee, meeting notes for this time period, several versions of the commission's strategic plan, and the annual report produced during her tenure. Of special importance are the results of a planning survey which was distributed to Commission for Women members in 1989. The collected information is neatly compiled and offers insight into the concerns of University women in the late 1980s.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Commission for Women.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
corpname; persname; geogname
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
University of Michigan. Commission for Women.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Commission for Women Twenty-Fifth Anniversary
  - Program and Invitation, 1996 (Box 1)
  - See also Audio Visual series (Box 1)
- Margaret Creger Records
  - Annual Report, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Commission for Women Retirement Subcommittee
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Data, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Expenditures, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Notes, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1991 ? (Box 1)
  - Mission and Strategic Plan, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Planning Survey, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
- Audio Visual
  - Hollenshead and Calkins--Commission for Women Brown Bag (Box 1)
  - March 18, 1997 (audio cassette tape) (Box 1)
  - Turnabout--Slide show at Commission for Women 25th Anniversary (Box 1)
  - 1996 (VHS video cassette) (Box 1)
  - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, November 20, 1996 (VHS video cassette) (Box 1)
Additional records for the Commission for Women spanning the years 1970 to 1985 can be found in the University of Michigan Affirmative Action Office record group, which is also held by the Bentley Historical Library.